# **Alexandros Efstratiou**

☑ alexandros.efstratiou.20@ucl.ac.uk • ⑤ alefstrat.github.io • in alex-efstra

#### **Profile**

I am a PhD Candidate in Computational Social Science in University College London's Computer Science Department with a background in social psychology and behavioral science. My research focuses on the interplay between polarization and misinformation on social media, and has been published in top-tier conferences like ACM WWW, ACM CSCW and AAAI ICWSM.

#### **Education**

#### University College London (UCL), Department of Computer Science

London, UK

PhD Computational Social Science (Center for Doctoral Training in Cybersecurity)

Sept 2020 – Present Topic: Propagation of misinformation through polarization on social media. I use methods such as:

- ▶ Machine learning classification (node classification using Graph Convolutional Networks, etc.)
- ▶ Community detection in online networks (Louvain algorithm, cluster analysis, etc.)
- ▶ User/community matching based on similarity metrics (cosine, Mahalanobis distance, etc.)
- ▶ Natural language processing (text classification, sentiment analysis, topic extraction, named entity recognition, etc.)
- Advanced statistical analysis (mixed-effects regression, structural equation modeling, etc.)
- ▶ Probability estimation and simulation (Markov Chains, binomial regression, etc.)
- ▶ Surveys, behavioral Randomized Controlled Trials (RCTs), and intervention testing

The project is supervised by Professor Emiliano De Cristofaro and Dr Tristan Caulfield and is funded by the UKRI's EPSRC.

#### **Durham University, Department of Psychology**

Durham, UK

MSc Behavioural Science, Distinction (79.20)/GPA 4.27 Cohort top performer

Sept 2019 - Sept 2020

University of East Anglia (UEA), School of Psychology BSc Psychology, First Class Honours (78.85)/GPA 4.25 Cohort top performer

Norwich, UK Sept 2016 – July 2019

#### **Publications**

- ▶ **Efstratiou, A.** (2024). Deliberate Exposure to Opposing Views and its Association with Behavior and Rewards on Political Communities. *To appear in the ACM Web Conference 2024 (WWW '24).*
- ▶ **Efstratiou, A.**, Blackburn, J., Caulfield, T., Stringhini, G., Zannettou, S., & De Cristofaro, E. (2023). Non-polar Opposites: Analyzing the Relationship between Echo Chambers and Hostile Intergroup Interactions on Reddit. *In the 17th International AAAI Conference on Web and Social Media (ICWSM '23).*
- ▶ **Efstratiou, A.**, & De Cristofaro, E. (2022). Adherence to Misinformation on Social Media Through Socio-Cognitive and Group-Based Processes. *Proceedings of the ACM on Human-Computer Interaction (CSCW '22)*.
- \*Hughes, J. P., **Efstratiou, A.**, Komer, S., Baxter, L., Vasiljevic, M., & Leite, A. C. (2022). The Impact of Risk Perceptions and Belief in Conspiracy Theories on COVID-19 Pandemic-Related Behaviours. *PLoS One*, 17(2), e0263716.

# **Pre-prints**

▶ **Efstratiou, A.**, Efstratiou, M., Yudhoatmojo, S., Blackburn, J., & De Cristofaro, E., (2023). "Here's Your Evidence": False Consensus in Public Twitter Discussions of COVID-19 Science. *Under submission*.

<sup>\*</sup>Joint first author.

#### **Invited Research Talks and Conference Talks**

- ▶ UCL Information Security Research Group 2024: What I see is all that's real: The dynamics of polarization and misinformation on social media platforms (invited research talk).
- ▶ UCR LOGOS group 2024: Uncovering a false consensus in public Twitter discussions of COVID-19 science (invited research talk).
- ▶ ICWSM 2023: Non-polar opposites: Analyzing the relationship between echo chambers and hostile intergroup interactions on Reddit (conference talk).
- ▶ GESIS 2023: Non-polar opposites: An examination of the interplay between echo chambers and hostile intergroup interactions online (invited research talk).
- ▶ CSCW 2022: Adherence to misinformation on social media through socio-cognitive and group-based processes (conference talk).
- ▶ Academy of Management Annual Meeting 2021: The leadership oversight bias in justice and hypocrisy evaluations of organisational diversity practices (conference talk).

### **Teaching**

- ▶ Teaching assistant: Cybersafety and Online Harms (MSc Course), UCL, Spring 2023-24
- ▶ Teaching assistant: People and Security (MSc Course), UCL, Fall 2023-24
- Teaching assistant: Probability, Statistics, & Modeling (BSc Course), UCL, Fall 2023-24
- → Teaching assistant: Evidence for Decision-Making (MPA Course), UCL, Fall 2022-23
- ▶ Guest lecturer: Evidence for Decision-Making (MPA Course), UCL, Fall 2022-23
- Guest lecturer: Social Cognition (BSc Course), Durham University, Spring 2019-20

#### **Service**

▶ Program Committee: ICWSM 2023-2024

Reviewer: DIS 2024, CHI 2024, CSCW 2023-2024, ICWSM 2022-2024, CogSci 2023, EPJ Data Science, S&P 2023, WWW 2023, NDSS 2023, IMC 2022

## Labs & Groups

Security and Privacy Advanced Lab, UCR/UCL  Doctoral Student	Riverside, CA/London, UK 2023 - Present
Digital Speech Lab, UCL Research Associate	London, UK 2023 – Present
National Research Centre on Privacy, Harm Reduction and Adversarial In Doctoral Researcher	nfluence Online UK 2020 – Present
International Data-driven Research for Advanced Modeling and Analysis Doctoral Researcher	(iDRAMA) Intl. 2020 – Present
Information Security Research Group (ISec), UCL	London, UK

#### Other experience

Doctoral Student

Fact-Check Cyprus (Part of CUT Social Computing Research Center)	Limassol, Cyprus (remote)
Fact-checker; FCC is an official EDMO member.	2023 – Present
Ogilvy UK	London, UK
Behavioural Science Practice Intern	July 2019
UEA Students' Union	Norwich, UK
Student Advocacy Assistant	2017 – 2019

2020 - Present

Norwich, UK June 2018 - July 2018

## **Awards & Honors**

- ▶ UCL EPSRC Doctoral Training Program Research Studentship
- ▶ Kurt Lewin prize as top performer in the 2019-2020 MSc Behavioural Science cohort, Durham University.
- ▶ British Psychological Society Prize for Outstanding Undergraduate Degree Performance as top performer of the BSc Psychology cohort at UEA in all three years of study.
- ▶ UEA School of Psychology prize for best undergraduate dissertation (overall) and best undergraduate dissertation (quantitative).

#### References

Emiliano De Cristofaro Professor, University of California, Riverside Computer Science & Engineering Department emilianodc@cs.ucr.edu

Gianluca Stringhini Associate Professor, Boston University Department of Electrical and Computer Engineering gian@bu.edu

Jeremy Blackburn Associate Professor, Binghamton University Department of Computer Science jblackbu@binghamton.edu